<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Curious Techizen</title>
    <description>A place for discussing anything tech. Old and new. Experiences and Opinions. Questions and rants. Primarily programming-related, but not exclusively.</description>
    <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://kiranrao.in/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 16:38:05 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 16:38:05 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Digital Identity Conundrum</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I look at why surrendering our digital identities to BigTech is a bad idea (with some examples). I then examine some potential solutions to the digital identity problem and the shortcomings of those solutions. I conclude by proposing my own solution, albeit still a far from perfect one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-doomsday-scenario&quot;&gt;The doomsday scenario&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you run a restaurant business. You operate a chain of outlets across the country . You’re doing great business for a few years. Then, one fine day, all of a sudden, you’re hit with a termination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are informed that you need to close your business because you violated a law, with the following additional points&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are not informed exactly what law you violated. You are only vaguely told that it is “something related to fire safety”, but not any more details.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not only are you supposed to close your business, you are not allowed to apply for a license for another business. Ever.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition to losing your business, you also lose your ID documents (passport, driving license, etc). Now you cannot drive, travel or transact with your bank.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These terminations apply not only to you, but also to some other businesses that were associated with you (some suppliers etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are desperate. You are no criminal, you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to obey the law. The only problem is you don’t know what to fix. You check your outlets for fire hazard standards, you ensure that the emergency exits are all functioning according to specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You approach the authorities, requesting more information. But all you receive in response is a vague automated reply that is no use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only have you lost your business, with no hope of starting another one, your entire life that is not even related to the business is destroyed as well. Your identity has been snatched from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;when-digital-identity-providers-are-gatekeepers&quot;&gt;When digital identity providers are gatekeepers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That opening section seems impossible, doesn’t it? Unless you are in an authoritarian state, it is unlikely that you will be handed out such an extreme punishment without even a chance at redemption. However, this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how it works in tech. Here’s a sampling of some situations where a mistake in the business can get your digital accounts in trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People have had their &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/android-news/google-just-terminated-our-start-up-google-play-publisher-account-on-christmas-day-5cb69a454da0&quot;&gt;developer accounts terminated&lt;/a&gt;, not because of any violation, but mereley on grounds of association. Yes, you read that right: Accounts have been terminated &lt;em&gt;merely on grounds of association&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People have had their YouTube accounts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/LivestreamFail/comments/dtv9g2/google_issues_account_permabans_for_many_of/&quot;&gt;permanently banned&lt;/a&gt; for flimsy reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your domain registrar &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gitbook.com/tech/post-mortems/06-20-gitbook-domains-blocked-by-registrar&quot;&gt;can suspend your domain&lt;/a&gt; based on suspicion (for example on suspicion that your domain is being used for phishing attacks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bans by themselves might not sound serious. Where it does get alarming is that these accounts are also tied to your digital identity. Did you notice that all the examples I provided above are Google accounts? When your Google Play or YouTube account is banned, so is your GMail account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what could happen if you suddenly lost access to your email account. Your email is the identity for all other services you use on the internet. Your bank, bill payment reminders, education services, password recovery mechanism, travel tickets, even governmental services - everything is tied to your email. It is the end of your digital identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you, but I like a lot of Google services. I use them day in and day out. The root of the problem here is not that the services are from Google. The problems are multi-fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The identity provider (in this case Google) is also the gatekeeper of some services (in this example, YouTube, Google Domains or Google Play).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The gatekeeper uses opaque algorithms to identify violations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The gatekeeper does not have effective redressal mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The gatekeeper is not regulated by law to improve the situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points 2 and 3 above relate to the false sense of “scalability”. See my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2020/12/15/scalable-tech-business/&quot;&gt;related post&lt;/a&gt; in that topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, remember that this problem is not only about bans. What happens if Google disappears one fine day? What happens to your digital identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, despite what the above examples might imply, this problem is not restricted to Google. It could just as well be any other bigtech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;work-arounds-that-dont-really-work&quot;&gt;Work-arounds that don’t really work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you protect yourself against this potential ban-hammer? There are some solutions but they are all not very effective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-different-google-account-for-business&quot;&gt;Use a different Google account for business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This solution involves using a different Google account, separate from your personal one, specifically for the business. This simply does not work (see termination by association above). Google does not disclose how it identifies the association. It could be IP-based. It could be all e-mail addresses associated with the same person. It could be anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-non-google-account-for-your-personal-email&quot;&gt;Use a non-Google account for your personal email.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might work but it has some downsides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You still have years of history tied to your GMail account and migrating them elsewhere is non-trivial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trusting a private corporation with your identity has the same risks as giving it to Google. That private tech company could ban your account in the same way as Google and that private company could disappear from business, leaving you stranded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-your-own-domain-and-own-email-address&quot;&gt;Use your own domain and own email address&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this might work but it has some downsides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The history and migration problems described in the previous solution apply&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cost and administrative effort involved in this solution are out of reach of most netizens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;governments-as-digital-identity-providers&quot;&gt;Governments as digital identity providers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proposed solution is that the responsibility of providing digital identity should be with &lt;strong&gt;Governments&lt;/strong&gt;. They are already responsible for our &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; identity documents. Passports, driving licenses, unique citizen numbers. This is just one more in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some ways in which this proposal is better than the existing solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Government issued identities are bound to be longer lived than a corporate-issued one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least in the democratic world, it is unlikely that you will be stripped of your identity without giving you a fair chance at redressal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Governments change, but your identity will remain. In other words, unlike corporates, Governments rarely go out of business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is far from perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For one, this will be a new identity, so migrating your history to it will still be a challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Governmental solutions are bound to be inferior in quality compared to corporate ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethical questions like surveillance are likely to come up when a Government is entrusted with digital identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We entrust too much in the hands of BigTech, including our whole identity in the digital world. Moving away is hard because of the inertia created by investment in the existing system. I proposed one solution that might work but does not address the inertia problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any solutions to this conundrum? You can comment using disqus below, or on twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ki_run/status/1421842364109402117?s=20&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/08/01/digital-identity-conundrum/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/08/01/digital-identity-conundrum/</guid>
        
        <category>digitalidentity</category>
        
        <category>bigtech</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Writing as a Problem Solving tool</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-history&quot;&gt;The history&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was new to StackOverflow, I was (to put it plainly) scared to ask a question there. The culture there was not exactly the most welcoming. People would downvote questions for no apparent reason, or even post comments or answers trivializing my question. I had very low points on StackOverflow and I did not want to risk losing points to downvotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did I cope? Well, I started to critique my own question before I posted it on StackOverflow. I started to try to anticipate how people would try to find fault with it, and try to fix those flaws in my question. This included things like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I make sure to check all official documentation and samples related to this topic?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the code sample reasonably complete? Can one just copy-paste it into the IDE and run it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the code example in my question cover all error cases?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is my question different from a similar-but-not-quite-the-same question that was already answered on StackOverflow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would then iterate over this. Surprisingly, I found that in a lot of cases, this process would lead me to the solution, without me having posted the question at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In more than 50% of the cases, when I start typing a question on StackOverflow, I find the answer even before I post it there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;beyond-stackoverflow&quot;&gt;Beyond StackOverflow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that this technique can be applied even outside of contexts that have a negative connotation. What started out as a self-defense mechanism turned into a general problem-solving technique. Now, I often apply the same idea whenever I get stuck with a problem. The steps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, I identify that to solve this problem I need to ask for help&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next, I write down the problem in as much detail as I can think of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then, I try to put myself in the shoes of the audience for this question. What details might they need for fixing the problem?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only if I do not solve the problem after iterating through Steps 2 and 3 a few times do I actually go ahead and post it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing is a great tool for problem-solving. Of course, it is not the only tool and is not applicable for all scenarios. For example, sometimes the huge level of detail could hide the problem and throw potential helpers off track. However when used in moderation, I find that it leads me to the solution without ever having to bother others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 15:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/07/31/writing-as-problem-solving/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/07/31/writing-as-problem-solving/</guid>
        
        <category>tipsntricks</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mobile Multiplatform and Me</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; This post is based on my own experience and is highly opinionated. It is not meant as a blanket “State of the Union” of mobile multiplatform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, there have been several attempts at cross-platform frameworks for building mobile (Android and iOS) apps. This post is about my experience with three of them: &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactnative.dev/&quot;&gt;ReactNative&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://flutter.dev/&quot;&gt;Flutter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://kotlinlang.org/lp/mobile/&quot;&gt;Kotlin Multiplatform Mobile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not meant as a competition. I’m not going to announce a winner at the end of the post. Every framework serves a different audience and has different use cases. I made sure to call out the sweet spot for each of these frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;react-native&quot;&gt;React Native&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RN was my first experience with mobile cross-platform. I worked with it in 2017 and at the time it was not very mature. However I expect things to have evolved since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concepts of React carry over directly. This makes mobile app development approachable for a large developer audience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Edit-refresh development cycle is very rapid compared to traditional mobile app development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ReactNative initially had only iOS support. Android was added later. This was obvious when I was working with it - Android frequently lagged behind iOS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ReactNative ultimately interpretes JavaScript code on the target platform. On Android this is achieved using a JS bridge, which makes it slow. It also results in “stringly-typed APIs” while crossing the bridge which kind of negates the productivity gains of the edit-refresh cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sweet-spot&quot;&gt;Sweet spot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sweet spot for RN is when you have web developers that want to get into mobile development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;kotlin-mobile-multiplatform&quot;&gt;Kotlin Mobile Multiplatform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with KMM in 2019-2020. At the time the technology was not very mature. At the time of writing this, it is still in Alpha. Do note that KMM is from JetBrains. My experience with JetBrains technology is that when it is designated as alpha, it is already very usable, even in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros-1&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KMM does not provide multiplatform UI libraries. It is intended to share logic, leaving writing the UIs to platform native code. This, in my opinion, is the correct approach to multiplatform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is from JetBrains, from the Kotlin team. Hence the tooling is great.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is Kotlin, which is my favourite language!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Due to the nature of KMM, you can share as little or as much of the code between platforms as you wish. You don’t give up on any of the platform native features.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t need to change the way you develop your Android app to make it multiplatform-capable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cons-1&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kotlin was a JVM language for several years. For mobile, you could interprete this as KMM being Android-first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While Kotlin, the language is very stable and mature, the KMM technology is still immature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KMM can be unnatural for iOS developers. The Kotlin-ObjC (and hence Kotlin-Swift) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Kotlin/comments/odau0p/marrying_kmm_and_swift_with_sourcery/h4056dq?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3&quot;&gt;interop has some limitations&lt;/a&gt; which can ruin the experience on the iOS consuming side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sweet-spot-1&quot;&gt;Sweet spot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sweet spots for KMM are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Android developers who have also dabbled in iOS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum Viable Products (MVPs). Remember point 5 from the pros of KMM. If you developed an app using KMM, and you later want to change your iOS app to become a pure native app, what you are left with is still a fully functional native Android app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;flutter&quot;&gt;Flutter&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not work professionally with Flutter. However, I made an open source app for learning Flutter in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros-2&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flutter is the most mature of the mobile cross-platform frameworks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hot reload! Seriously. Flutter’s hot-reload is life-changing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mature implementations of several libraries (especially those from Google like Maps, Analytics etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cons-2&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dart is a dated language compared to Kotlin, Swift or TypeScript. This could have something to do with Dart’s history of a compile-to-JS language that dramatically pivoted to mobile multiplatform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing platform plugins for Flutter is not as natural as plugging into native functionality with KMM’s expect/actual mechanism. It used to be stringly-typed but that seems to have changed with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pub.dev/packages/pigeon&quot;&gt;pigeon package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sweet-spot-2&quot;&gt;Sweet spot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sweet spot for Flutter is for teams that want end-to-end cross platform apps without having to go through the mess of the web development ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the mobile multiplatform frameworks have their use cases, and each have their sore weaknesses. Mobile cross-platform is still very much an unsolved problem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2021 16:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/07/24/mobile-multiplatform/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/07/24/mobile-multiplatform/</guid>
        
        <category>multiplatform</category>
        
        <category>flutter</category>
        
        <category>android</category>
        
        <category>ios</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Basic before advanced</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a non-programming post in the series I call “re-stating the obvious”. This series talks about topics that already boast extensive literature, I’m merely adding my own annotations. You can find all posts in this series &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/obvious&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-anectode&quot;&gt;An anectode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start this post with an anecdote. The era was 1990s and the scene was a bus stand. While my father and I were waiting for a bus, a hawker approached us with a bunch of imitation Casio watches. Here’s the conversation that ensued:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Father:&lt;/strong&gt; How much for that watch?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hawker:&lt;/strong&gt; 100 rupees
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;F:&lt;/strong&gt; That is a lot for a watch. Why is it so expensive?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;H:&lt;/strong&gt; It has a lot of amazing features …
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;F:&lt;/strong&gt; Like what?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;H:&lt;/strong&gt; See this button here? It activates the stop watch … and look, it glows in the dark … and also, it is water resistant … and oh, do you see the strap? It is reversible .. and …
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;F:&lt;/strong&gt; I see the watch is running behind by 5 minutes. Why is that?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;H:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh that is probably because the light and stopwatch consume a lot of battery
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;F:&lt;/strong&gt; So you are trying to sell me a watch that does not even tell the time correctly but has lot of other useless fancy features?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-creep&quot;&gt;Feature creep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia has a great definition of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feature_creep&quot;&gt;featue creep&lt;/a&gt;. To paraphrase it, and add my own flavor to the definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Feature creep is the tendency to add advanced features to a system even before the main purpose of the existence of the system is fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say “system” but feature creep could also occur in a narrower scope, i.e., a subsystem of a system (more on this in a bit). Let’s take a look at some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;smartphones&quot;&gt;Smartphones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A smartphone is perhaps the obvious example that comes to mind. Smartphones function as calculators, cameras, navigation devices, alarms, calendars, books, entertainment devices and a whole bunch more. With so much functionality crammed in, the fundamental purpose of making and receiving phone calls has taken a back seat. All the other features use up resources like battery, leaving very little for actual phone calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;automotive-systems&quot;&gt;Automotive systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the automotive space, the line between what is infotainment and what is driver-assist is constantly blurring. What is a luxury today becomes a basic safety feature tomorrow. It is no wonder that companies get carried away trying to pack their vehicles to the brim with features This is where things start going awry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Feature creep starts seeping in such a way that safety features of one subsystem are rendered almost useless due to overcrowded features in another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this. Let’s say you have a vehicle with every major driver assist safety feature that you can think of: Tyre pressure monitoring system, Anti-lock Braking system, Side-stand alert, cruise control, collision warning - you name it. And then, you go and pair this with an infotainment system that distracts the driver, or requires the driver to spend too much time fiddling with the controls in order to achieve anything. What use are all those advanced features then? &lt;strong&gt;The feature creep in the infotainment subsystem could cause fatal crashes long before the safety subsystem can even kick in.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think this is hypothetical, think again. Next time you use your vehicle, check how easy it is to perform some tasks like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the destination of your navigation system while you are driving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking the tyre pressure (if your vehicle is equipped with a TPMS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you use phone projection systems like Android Auto or Apple CarPlay, how seamlessly does the system recover from a lost connection between the vehicle and phone?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And note that this list does not even include the “tainment” part of infotainment. I have not even gotten to the part where you try to control your music or podcasts or message someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basic-first&quot;&gt;Basic First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not here to advocate that there is one true solution to this problem. I’m a fan of the “a product should do one thing and do it well” philosophy but it does not apply to every product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What might be interesting is to come up with some principles for a threshold for a feature to make it in. This tweet about Minimum Viable Product comes to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Debunking the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MVP?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#MVP&lt;/a&gt; myth: a key figure from &amp;quot;The Lean Product Playbook&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/TvuHbBnE7e&quot;&gt;http://t.co/TvuHbBnE7e&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/leanstartup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#leanstartup&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/prodmgmt?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#prodmgmt&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/DqM0tWPzLG&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DqM0tWPzLG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dan Olsen (@danolsen) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danolsen/status/613581087617384449?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 24, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be an interesting experiment to repurpose (and kind of negate) the second image in this tweet and use it as a template for deciding if a feature should be added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bottom of the pyramid (Functionality): Will absence of this feature prevent the core functionality of the feature from being fulfilled?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second from the bottom (Reliability): Without this feature, will the reliability of the product be impacted?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second from top (Usability): Does absence of this feature have detrimental effect on the usability of the core product?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Top of the pyramid (Delight): Only if the product passes through the other three filters, then ask the question - Do we have no way to delight the user without this feature?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to all these questions is a resounding Yes, then the feature makes it in, else it stays out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of restating the obvious, &lt;strong&gt;advanced features are useless if the basic ones don’t work well&lt;/strong&gt;. Products ought to focus on the basic reason for their existence to work solidly before trying to add more. Otherwise it risks being perceived as gimmicky.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 16:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/21/basic-first/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/21/basic-first/</guid>
        
        <category>obvious</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Facebook and Privacy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that using Facebook is detrimental to one’s privacy. However, not everyone is in a position to quit the platform. In this post, I look into some steps that I took while attempting to use Facebook with minimal intrusion to my privacy. Your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-mobile-app&quot;&gt;Facebook mobile app&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the Facebook Android app for a long time and for some startling reason, I realized that I had granted it several permissions. My first step towards setting things right was to revoke every single permission that I had granted it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean in practice though?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can no longer upload pictures to FB directly from my phone. Which is actually a blessing in disguise. I use my laptop for that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… that is all!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook had a bazillion permissions, including Contacts, camera, storage and what not. And the single gain it brought me was the ability to upload photos! I can live without that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time I also used the Facebook Lite app - it is a slimmed down version and uses less storage space and data. Still, I made sure to not give it any permissions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-rid-of-the-app&quot;&gt;Getting rid of the app&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just having the app installed is enough to compromise on your privacy. In slightly older verisons of Android, &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; app can know what other apps are installed on a phone (without any permission). Using this, it is possible to “fingerprint” a device. You can read more about fingerprinting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/features/block-fingerprinting/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to get rid of the app altogether. This comes with some minor inconveniences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I no longer get notifications when someone sends me a friend request or comments on my posts. This is actually a good thing (I’ll probably write a separate post about taming notifications some day)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can no longer share something directly to Facebook. I often come across interesting articles and use Android’s Share functionality to share it on Twitter and Facebook. This requires the app to be installed and after getting rid of the app, I have to log in on a browser and paste the link manually. This is something I’m ready to live with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;browsing-on-the-desktop-firefox&quot;&gt;Browsing on the desktop: Firefox&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it is still possible for Facebook to track me on the web. &lt;strong&gt;Even if I’m not logged in to Facebook&lt;/strong&gt;. All I need to do is visit a website that includes a “Like” or “Share” button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To really make it difficult for Facebook to track me while I’m browsing, I use Mozilla Firefox with the dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/facebook-container/&quot;&gt;“Facebook container” plugin&lt;/a&gt;. This is an official plugin from Mozilla. What it does is, it tries to isolate my Facebook activity on the web from my non-Facebook activity. I’ve been using it for a couple of months now and it just works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;browsing-on-android-firefox-focus&quot;&gt;Browsing on Android: Firefox Focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my phone, I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.mozilla.focus&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;gl=US&quot;&gt;Firefox Focus&lt;/a&gt; browser, which is a browser by Mozilla, but is different from Firefox itself. This browser is also available for iOS and even for desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat like Incognito mode in Chrome, except it is better. It not only deletes all cookies as soon as you close the browser, it also blocks several trackers by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do I use it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever I want to browse Facebook on my phone, I just browse to the website on Firefox Focus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since I’m in the EU, I’m first presented with some cookie consent - which I accept (because the cookies will be deleted anyway). This step will not apply if I’m outside the EU.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then I login with my username and password (I use Android’s auto-fill for this purpose).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After browsing, I logout and hit the big “delete” button. Done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is marginally more work than having the app installed, but it has actually benefited me. I spend way less time on Facebook now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to use Facebook without entirely letting go of my privacy. It introduces some friction but in my personal experience, it has only resulted in a net gain for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a post in my series related to digital privacy. You can read more posts in this series &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/privacy&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For more advanced information and inspiration about digital privacy, you can visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacytools.io/&quot;&gt;Privacy Tools&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 17:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/20/facebook-privacy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/20/facebook-privacy/</guid>
        
        <category>privacy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Moving to Counter for analytics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Analytics is often crucial for a business. This includes web anaytics, app analytics and everything in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for a simple blog like this one, there is no need for advanced analytics. These are the features that would be nice to have. Note that these are restricted to &lt;em&gt;page&lt;/em&gt; analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many hits has my blog received, page-wise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What was the source of the hits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, what I &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; need is &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt; analytics. This means things like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tracking new versus returning users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tracking a user’s flow through my blog (they landed on this page and then went to this other page and finally exited from this page)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Google Analytics all this while for this blog, but today I have decided to move away from it. The reason is that GA provides advanced features but this comes at a cost. It uses cookies and this comes at a cost, not for my privacy, but that of the readers of my blog. It is totally unfair for me to compromise on the privacy of my readers for no tangible benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now I have installed &lt;a href=&quot;https://counter.dev/&quot;&gt;Counter&lt;/a&gt;. Counter is a privacy friendly web analytics service and it is open source. It is also very simple and has very few features, not more than what I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how often I update this blog, I might even consider removing analytics altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next up:&lt;/strong&gt; My comments system (I need to evaluate whether I need this disqus commenting system at all)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;Footnote&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for businesses, there are privacy-friendly alternatives to traditional analytics engines. I want to end this post by advocating against analytics engine that invade your users’ privacy. We can do better and our users deserve better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 18:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/13/privacy-friendly-analytics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2021/03/13/privacy-friendly-analytics/</guid>
        
        <category>privacy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>UI ≠ UX</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;und&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/R8DfByhDJL&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/R8DfByhDJL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rachel Appel (@RachelAppel) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RachelAppel/status/1168905856773230594?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 3, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a non-programming post in the series I call “re-stating the obvious”. This series talks about topics that have been discussed at length, I’m just making my own observations about them. You can find all posts in this series &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/obvious&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not a designer, so please take the opinions in this post with a pinch of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ui-and-ux&quot;&gt;UI and UX&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good user interface is a user acquisition tool, while a good user experience is a user retention tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it differently, a good user interface attracts users to your system, while a good user experience gets users to keep using your system. A couple of important observations about this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neither is a subset of the other; a good UI does not necessarily translate to good UX and it is possible to have a good UX while the UI is poor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both of these are important; their relative importance depends on the nature of the system (more on this when we discuss some examples in a minute).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-ui-not-so-good-ux&quot;&gt;Good UI, not so good UX&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at some examples where UI is good, but UX not so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatic soap dispensers:&lt;/strong&gt; I got one for myself because it worked great when I tried it (It had a great UI). However during everyday use, I realized that it dispenses too much soap and that causes a mess near the sink. It has a poor UX.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xcode:&lt;/strong&gt; All those “poof” animations looks so sleek (amazing UI) but they completely and utterly destroy the overall IDE experience (unacceptably poor UX). So many actions rely on gimmicky gestures and are completely undiscoverable (how do you remove a breakpoint that you set in XCode? Clue: It is not “right click and remove” like every other sane IDE on the planet)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In-car controls:&lt;/strong&gt; Multi-function controls on the steering wheels give them such a futuristic look. Those buttons on the infotainment console looks straight out of a spaceship. Amazing UI. But, how many times do you need to click on the steering wheel button to achieve a certain task? How reliably can you turn on or off the defogger using the center console? Can you do all of this without taking your eyes off the road?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a reason I chose that last example. Imagine an ill-thought out UX that causes a driver to take their eyes off the road for even a couple of seconds at three-digit speeds. The consequences can be disastrous, even death. This is compounded by the fact that the &lt;em&gt;problems with the UX are often not discoverable&lt;/em&gt; until it is too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goes back to the relative importance part. The In-car controls example above is an instance where UX ought to be given a lot more importance than just UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-ux-with-mediocre-ui&quot;&gt;Good UX with mediocre UI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some examples of systems where the UX is good but UI not so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevators:&lt;/strong&gt; The elevator in my apartment is old-fashioned and … how do I say this … &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt;. It is not really welcoming in appearance. However, it just works. All the buttons are intuitive, it is disabled-friendly with braille buttons and you just cannot go wrong using it. The UX is near-perfect even though the UI does leave a lot to be desired.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Older cars:&lt;/strong&gt; My first car was very low on features, but now that I look back I have to admit the UX for the driver was fantastic. It had barely any features but whatever little it did, was a breeze to operate. The only control on the steering wheel was the horn, the stalks on the steering wheel column only had the light, indicators and wiper controls. The Air conditioner and defogger were trivial to operate without taking my eyes off the road, even in the dark. Fantastic UX, not an inviting UI at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git:&lt;/strong&gt; (Uh oh .. I failed in my resolve to not include any programming related examples). Git is an indispensable tool for programmers and makes our lives so much easier. The whole experience of cheap branching, not requiring a network to work and more make it orders of magnitude better than its predecessors like CVS. However, the commands are named rather weirdly. Worse, some commands do very different things compared to what they did in previous source control systems like SVN. Incredibly good UX, a UI that leaves a lot to be desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This category probably has a lot more examples than the first. Think of all the things around you that just work even though they are not particularly attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UI ≠ UX. In my limited experience, UI is given more importance than UX. In my opinion this is counter-productive in the long run, both for businesses and users.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 17:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/20/ui-not-ux/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/20/ui-not-ux/</guid>
        
        <category>obvious</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tech as an Enhancer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a non-programming post in the series I call “re-stating the obvious”. This series talks about topics that have been beaten to pulp already. I’m simply adding to the cacophony. You can find all posts in this series &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/obvious&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-trigger-for-this-post&quot;&gt;The trigger for this post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, some Amazon Web Services servers suffered an outage that caused a domino effect across countless products and services which depend on AWS. Social media was quick to poke fun at the incident with an explosion of jokes and memes. This tweet is a summary of the mood of social media on that day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I... can&amp;#39;t vacuum... because us-east-1 is down.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Geoff Belknap (@geoffbelknap) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/geoffbelknap/status/1331690657170157568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 25, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learnt&quot;&gt;Lessons learnt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take-away from this incident (and others before it) is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most products and services ought to dwell on the role of technology in the system. Does tech bring the most value as an &lt;em&gt;enhancer&lt;/em&gt; or as a &lt;em&gt;prerequisite&lt;/em&gt;? In other words, &lt;strong&gt;does the system degrade gracefully&lt;/strong&gt; in the absence of the very tech that differentiates it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(In this post, I use the term “tech” in a very loose sense)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at some (mostly hypothetical) examples. Since I spent a large portion of my career in two domains (IoT and automobile), some bias is bound to creep into the examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is awesome that my air-conditioner is connected to the internet. I can set the temperature on my way home so that the house is already comfortable when I reach there. But should it really &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; the internet to function? Do I absolutely have to configure the WiFi settings &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; using the air-conditioner?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An internet-connected blood pressure monitor is a really good idea since it eliminates the manual data entry process and lets medical personnel have direct access to the necessary data. However, a blood pressure monitor that &lt;em&gt;refuses to function when a server is down&lt;/em&gt; is not very useful, is it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can unlock my car with my phone? Amazing. Does it also have a good old key for backup? It would be awkward if my &lt;em&gt;phone is out of battery and I cannot even unlock the car&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last point seems far-fetched but it really isn’t. It is just one step away from this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Got in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Zipcar?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Zipcar&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;#39;ve been driving for 3 days. It doesn&amp;#39;t start. Call Zipcar and get told that the car can&amp;#39;t access the internet so it won&amp;#39;t start. The only option is to have a tow truck come and tow it to somewhere where it has internet.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Keith Smiley (@SmileyKeith) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SmileyKeith/status/1078417333540990976?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on with dozens of examples but I think I’ve illustrated my point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;offline-first&quot;&gt;Offline first&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offlinefirst.org/&quot;&gt;“Offline-first”&lt;/a&gt; is often used to describe apps that function when the network is unavailable, but it is more than that. Offline-first apps also behave well in the face of a &lt;em&gt;poor network connection&lt;/em&gt;. As an end user, the experience when you have that feeble network is way worse than when you have no network at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept of offline-first can be extended to all things tech. In majority of the cases, solutions need to be designed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt; for the situation where the tech crutch on which the solution depends is unavailable for whatever reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then&lt;/strong&gt; for the case where the tech is available but in a significantly reduced form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then and only then&lt;/strong&gt; for the case where the differentiating technology is healthy and functioning at its peak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do qualify all my opinions with “majority of” or “most of” because I’m pretty sure there are situations where this is not feasible. I know there must be some solutions out there that rely completely on the tech, where the solution ceases to exist without the tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech is making its mark in unimaginable ways in unprecedented fields. It works really well when it enhances an existing system. It would be a shame to go overboard and make a system overly reliant on tech where there is no real need to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 21:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/18/tech-enhancer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/18/tech-enhancer/</guid>
        
        <category>obvious</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scalable tech ≠ scalable business</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a non-programming post in the series I call “re-stating the obvious”. This series talks about topics that are nothing new, a lot has been said and written about these topics already. I’m simply putting it in my own words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find all posts in this series &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags/obvious&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Be sure to check back because more posts will be added in this series over the coming period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-scalable&quot;&gt;What exactly is “scalable”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalability&quot;&gt;wikipedia definition&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalability&lt;/strong&gt; is the property of a system to handle a growing amount of work by adding resources to the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the initial stages of my career, a tech lead once described a scalable system in layman terms to me as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A scalable system is one where by adding just a small amount effort or resources you can increase the output or gain by a large amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real-life (albeit silly) example I like to cite is cooking rice versus making rotis. Cooking rice is scalable because you don’t need to double the effort in order to cook double the amount of rice. On the other hand, if you want to double the number of rotis, you need to (more or less) double the effort. Making rotis, is thus not scalable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scalable-tech&quot;&gt;Scalable tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In technology terms, scalability refers to the ability to handle more users, requests, traffic etc without the system hitting its limits. Let’s say you create a system that can handle 1 million users with a team of 100 engineers. If you want to increase your target 10 fold to 10 million, you should not need to employ 10 times as many engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software industry has brought about a revolution in massively scalable technology. We routinely see CXOs of tech giants at their respective annual conferences reeling off staggering statistics about their products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X million concurrent users per second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Y billion total active users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Z terabytes of data served per day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and so on …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is no mean feat, mind you. Achieving this scale is a humongous engineering effort that requires coordintation between countless moving parts (from the software stack to the OS to the hardware to the network, even ventilation, cooling and geopolitical factors come into play). It is a marvel, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does this translate to a scalable business? For example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does the cost for manual fallbacks increase with the problem size for a business based on &lt;strong&gt;algorithmic decisions&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the cost of mistakes when the business relies on &lt;strong&gt;content moderation&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How well does the tech mesh with the need for global &lt;strong&gt;regulatory compliance&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scalable-business&quot;&gt;Scalable business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A scalable business refers to one that can expand (for example to multiple geographies) with just an increment in investment (in terms of cost or effort).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing industry has shown the world how to conduct a globally scalable business for decades. Here are some examples&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every country has differing standards when it comes to &lt;strong&gt;automobile industry&lt;/strong&gt;. This includes factors like pollution limits, safety features like seat belts, airbags, ISOFix and more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norway is very strict about speed limits. So much so that cars sold in Norway are &lt;strong&gt;required to calibrate the speedometer&lt;/strong&gt; to show the speed as 10% more than the actual speed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every country has differing standards regarding &lt;strong&gt;consumer electrical and electronic equipment&lt;/strong&gt;. Refrigerators, air conditioners, microwave ovens etc have to adhere to different standards of energy consumption, fluctuations, even noise requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some countries like South Korea require that cellphone cameras should always have the &lt;strong&gt;shutter sound permanently enabled&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of these differences, we see the automotive, consumer electronics and other industries comply with these local requirements. These industries have built scalable businesses that work with differing local policies around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scalable-tech--scalable-business&quot;&gt;Scalable tech ≠ scalable business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the tech industry does not seem to have learnt from the manufacturing industry. Here are a few examples that illustrate the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mobile-app-stores&quot;&gt;Mobile app stores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile app stores are grappling with the problem of app approvals. Approvals take weeks or even months and this is a major pain point for businesses that wish to publish apps on the stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story doesn’t end there. At least one of the big mobile app stores has serious problems with automated app removals. If you are a mobile app developer, chances are you have come across multiple instances of apps being removed for no apparent reason, and developers not being given a fair chance at redressal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This here is a classic example of confusing the scalability of the tech for scalability of the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The app review algorithms are great piece of scalable technology. Unfortunately, the same algorithms come in the way of a scalable business because the business has been designed around not requiring much manual review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;content-moderation&quot;&gt;Content moderation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social networks, video platforms and similar platforms have a problem very similar to mobile app stores, except the stumbling block is content moderation. Some examples of situations where the scale failed the business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media used for interference in the electoral process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misinformation campaigns on social media, ranging from incorrect information about Covid-19 vaccines to using social media to whip up mob frenzy (remember all the lynching incidents across the world in 2018-2020?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gory incidents telecast live over various video streaming platforms (remember Christchurch shootings in 2019?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some platforms have scrambled to “fix” some of these problems (some social networks added “labels” to disputed posts etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But these seem to be band-aid. The real problem is that the products themselves are not built for real scale (beyond the technology itself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulatory-compliance&quot;&gt;Regulatory compliance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know what happened with user data (in the scandal-that-shall-not-be-named involving the social-network-that-also-shall-not-be-named). But that is just part of the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several countries are now coming up with regulations around privacy of the data of their citizens. Some are taking it a step further and proposing rules that dictate where the data of their citizens should physically reside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real problem here is tech companies building their business models around regulations that existed &lt;em&gt;when the product was conceptualized&lt;/em&gt;, and failing to foresee that regulations will catch up eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the products scale really well from a purely technical standpoint, but leave a lot to be desired when the rubber meets the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure I just scratched the surface - of both sides of the coin. There are dozens more examples of business scaling done right; and dozens more where they fall short despite a stellar tech stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, at the risk of re-stating the obvious, &lt;strong&gt;A scalable tech stack is necessary but not sufficient for running a scalable business&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 19:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/15/scalable-tech-business/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/12/15/scalable-tech-business/</guid>
        
        <category>obvious</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Falsehoods programmers believe about addresses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the better part of the last three years developing a navigation app at work. It includes features like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Searching for a location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding a location to favorites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn by turn navigation to a destination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the seemingly simple task of splitting an address into two parts for displaying in the user interface (line 1 and line 2). The exact mechanism of the split didn’t matter as long as it could be reasonably split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here as some examples of how I presumed it could be split depending on the length of the address&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Line 1 = Place Name; Line 2 = address&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Line 1 = Place name, number, street; Line 2 = city, state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Line 1 = Place name, number; Line 2 = street, city&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple, right? Wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course, I’ve made several assumptions about addresses that turned out to be incorrect. This post attempts to list the things I learned about addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is inspired by other “Falsehood programmers believe” posts (and hence uses a similar format). In fact, there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kdeldycke/awesome-falsehood&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; that lists all such posts. Other people before me have already made “Falsehoods about addresses” lists, but I’m making one based on my own experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s get right to the falsehoods. Every one of the statements below is false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About &lt;strong&gt;locations&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every location has a unique address. This is false: every location has a unique &lt;em&gt;geocoordinate&lt;/em&gt; (lat-long), or other such &lt;em&gt;identifier&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.google.com/pluscodes/&quot;&gt;Google Plus Codes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://what3words.com/about-us/&quot;&gt;what3words&lt;/a&gt;, but it does not have a unique &lt;em&gt;address&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A location has an address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About &lt;strong&gt;addresses&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The concept of an address is universal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What constitutes an address is universal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has a number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address identifies a single house/shop/office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has a street name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has a post code/zip code/pin code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has a neighborhood/locality name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has a place name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address is hierarchical (number, street, city, state, country)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User interface&lt;/strong&gt; related:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address has sufficient info to make sense in a user interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address, when shortened (ellipsized etc) to fit on a user interface, still gives enough context to the user&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An address fits on one screen on a mobile phone with a readable font size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About &lt;strong&gt;streets&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A street has a name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A street name is unique in a city&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A street name is unique in a locality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A road number (like highway number) is unique in a locality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A road number uniquely identifies a road&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A neighborhood/locality name is unique in a city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About &lt;strong&gt;directions&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What constitutes a navigation instruction is universal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A navigation instruction at a point is unambiguous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restrictions applied to navigation (like avoid highways, avoid tolls etc) are unambiguous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Navigation directions are user-friendly (this one is an opinion, and not a fact)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/10/24/falsehoods-about-addresses/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://kiranrao.in/blog/2020/10/24/falsehoods-about-addresses/</guid>
        
        <category>falsehoods</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
